<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preacht at St Maries in Oxford, the 5. of August: 1624. Concerning the kingdomes peace. By Iohn Randol B: in D: of Brasen-nose Colledge</title>
            <author>Randal, John, b. 1594 or 5.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10401</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20685</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102398</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838183</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10401)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1078:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preacht at St Maries in Oxford, the 5. of August: 1624. Concerning the kingdomes peace. By Iohn Randol B: in D: of Brasen-nose Colledge</title>
                  <author>Randal, John, b. 1594 or 5.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Lichfield and William Turner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2548:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHT AT S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MARIES IN OXFORD, the 5. of Auguſt: 1624. Concerning the <hi>Kingdomes Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY IOHN RANDOL B: in D: of <hi>Braſen-noſe</hi> Colledge.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omne quod eſt, tam diu eſt, quamdiù unum eſt; ens enim &amp; unum convertuntur:</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Tis a Principle in the METAPHYSICKS.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>If their hearts be diuided, they ſhall be found guiltie, and then followes deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <bibl>HOSEA 10.2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by IOHN LICHFIELD and WILLIAM TVRNER. 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:2548:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2548:2"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MARKE 3.24.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And if a Kingdome be diuided againſt it ſelfe, that Kingdome cannot ſtand.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Chool-controuerſies mixt with points of deuotion I ſometimes deliuer'd from this place; but now a Text that requires the diuinity of a Prince, and th'expoſition of a Souldier, rather then a Schoole: Yet-no man ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize this Text, himſelfe, or mee: was not our Sauiour an Oratour vpon't? and if our Sauiour himſelfe handle the Common-wealth 'tis poſſible then to be diuinely handled: and if diuinely handled, it can looſe nothing by the handling: <hi>If a Kingdome bee &amp;c.</hi> Wherein you may pleaſe to obſerue, a <hi>State,</hi> the <hi>Qualitie</hi> of ſuch a State, and the <hi>effects</hi> of ſuch qualities: the State not of a priuate man, but the Compound aggregate State of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Kingdome: <hi>a Kingdome;</hi> that's certaine: then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the Quality, or caſuall actions of ſuch a State, they are diuiſions againſt themſelues; and they are vncertaine; <hi>If a Kingdome be diuided againſt it ſelfe; If diuided,</hi> that's vncertaine: Thirdly, the Iſſues and euill events of ſuch diuiſions, &amp; that's not-ſtanding ſhall I ſay? nay, 'tis non-poſſibility of ſtanding, and that's too-too certaine, God knowes: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>it cannot ſtand if it be diuided;</hi> that it cannot. To handle the State by it ſelfe, and the caſualtie of ſuch a State after that; and ſo conclude with th'effects of all, were a pretty playing me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2548:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
fit for eaſing of the breath; but very vnfit for the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſcuſſion of the Cauſe: wee muſt collect the whole, <hi>A diuided Kingdome cannot ſtand.</hi> Had the time bin as royall as the Text, I could haue entertain'd yee all; but no — Yet not like thoſe who profeſſing a glorious magnitude are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in moſt inferiour things: for I will open that vnt'ee, which euery man will not vnfold; Treaſon againſt a King as a bloud-guiltie ſinne, but againſt a Kingdome as much more, as any whole is greater then its part: Loe, I preſent vnt'ee the Changes of States, deſolations of Kingdomes, the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of the whole full of Intemperance, vniuſtice, auarice, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and whatſoeuer herein almoſt is worthy to be known; I preſent the cauſes and th'effects, together with the remedies of all, not without ſome more eſpeciall application to the time; only be fauourable I pray, to this too much extempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſitie of the man; ſo farre as the ſingle nature of the Cauſe will beare, you ſhall haue nothing more nor leſſe, then the diuiſion of a Kingdome will afford. <hi>If a Kingdome be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided againſt it ſelfe, that kingdome cannot ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Prophet would fore-tell th'expiration of the Iewiſh reigne, he prophecies of diſſenſions-ſhall ariſe; <hi>The Childe againſt th'auncient, the baſe againſt the Honourable:</hi> Eſay 3. chap. 5. ver. and it followes in a moment after; <hi>Ceci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit Hieruſalem, the Kingdome is fallen,</hi> i'th' 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ver: diuide it, and it falls: it came to paſſe (<hi>Ioſephus</hi> giues it) in three deadly Sects, whoſe chiefes were <hi>Simon, Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Eleazar:</hi> By ciuill diſcord did <hi>Carthage</hi> fall; by the like did old <hi>Rome</hi> her Empire ruine; while their diſſention gaue entrance to the Turke; the Kingdomes of <hi>Hungarie, Rhodes,</hi> and other many States, haue felt the torment of this Text: what needes any more? Interpreters ſay all, 'tis a popular argument our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vſeth, and too-too wel knowne of all, that a diuided king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome cannot ſtand; <hi>If a Kingdome bee diuided againſt it ſelfe, that Kingdome cannot ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As th'eſſence of God is one, ſo it behooues all things to be vnite, that will ſubſiſt in him: take the moſt comely body in this learned Crowne of men, and diuide either the ſpirits or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2548:3"/>
humours of that body one againſt another, and neither beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor body can long ſubſiſt: out of the beauteous fabricke of the World, if ye take that excellent correſpondence away, whereby the Caeleſtiall Spheares, and the inferiour Elements doe louingly agree together, the World it ſelfe can neuer long endure: except <hi>the heauens heare th'earth, and th'earth the heauens,</hi> and both agree vnto the prouiſion of the whole, the World it ſelfe can neuer well ſubſiſt: <hi>Hoſea 2.21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The demonſtrance is as plaine; becauſe diuiſion deſtroyes the very <hi>Forme</hi> it ſelfe: as if ye diuide a man, there remaines no longer <hi>forma hominis,</hi> but <hi>forma cadaveris:</hi> ſo if ye diuide a Common-wealth, there remaines no longer the forme of a good Common-wealth; but the forme of barbarouſneſſe and folly doth remaine: there may reſult out of ſuch a diuiſion, two armies of ſouldiers, two parties of a faction; but meane time, the faire, proper, entire bulke and beauty of a kingdome is deſtroyed: that cannot ſtand: which is the <hi>emphaſis</hi> of the Text: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that kingdome cannot ſtand. Neither were it of much conſequence, if it deſtroyed forme alone; but it pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes <hi>matter</hi> together with the <hi>forme:</hi> diuiſion weakens the ſtrongeſt publicke State that is: diuiſion calls in the forreine diſcontents of other Realmes: diuiſion turnes ſwords of the ſame mans making one againſt anothers point: diuiſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes the very <hi>end,</hi> for which a Kingdome was ordain'd: For the very prime ordinance of a kingdome was, to vnite all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one Head, one Law, one liberty, one profit and pleaſure of good life, that ſo the vnity being equally intereſted among all, all might with one accord more ſtrongly combine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt the auarices, ambitions, tyrannies of other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching men: for the World will neuer want <hi>Nimrods:</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Oeconomicall hunters</hi> there be, that hunt for the prouiſion of their owne houſes; and as many <hi>Venatores Politici,</hi> that hunt after other mens Kingdomes: and therefore, <hi>vae ſi divida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> woe vnto that Kingdome is diuided; for the hunter will take it: <hi>If a Kingdome be diuided againſt it ſelfe, that Kingdome cannot ſtand:</hi> Wherefore, be we all vnited as firme as fleſh is to the bone, cemented all together in loue, glewed vnto the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2548:4"/>
publick welfare of the ſtate: If any diuiſions haue amongſt vs bin, if any fallacy of ſelfe-loue, if any poiſon of debate, it muſt be ſo no more: Ile open the remedies, doe but you make righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous iudgement, whether they bee not better then the diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>Some haue taken occaſion to contriue a diuiſion vpon meere REVENGE; ſo <hi>Coriolanus</hi> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> being exaſperated by an vniuſt condemnation, did deriue the warre vpon his owne Countrey: So baniſht <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> how did he diſcouer the whole Councell of <hi>Athens</hi> to th'enemy? What a combuſtion did he make betweene th'Oligarchye, and the Commonalty? So much <hi>revenge</hi> will doe; and more then ſo; for ſmaller iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, though they be no poſitiue euills, but privatiues only; as the tenne Tribes againſt <hi>Dauid,</hi> becauſe he afforded <hi>Iuda</hi> all the honour of attendance at repoſſeſſion to his Crowne, and did not ſend as honourable a ſummons to invite them of <hi>Iſrael</hi> alſo; therefore <hi>in fierceneſſe they aroſe,</hi> pleaded proportion, number, valour, abuſe of all; and a great diuiſion, a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion did they cauſe, <hi>2 Sam. 19.</hi> and <hi>20</hi> chap. So much a litle diſtaſte, a <hi>priuatiue</hi> diſhonour can produce: and the remedy is, whether they be iuſtly or vniuſtly puniſht; Superiours, Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, to intreate all: Superiours, their authority I intreat to diſtribute their face and lawfull fauour as proportionably as they can. Giue tenne Tribes the reſpect of ten, &amp; two that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to two; giue fiue hundred Counties the honour of fiue hundred, &amp; to the leſſe number the leſſe fauour doth pertaine. 'Tis lawfull peradventure to fauour theſe, not thoſe, where both doe equally deſerue; but 'tis not expedient ſo to doe: For a litle diſtaſte, a great diuiſion may ariſe: <hi>Achitophell</hi> will diuert, and many a Politician moe, vnleſſe they be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: on th'other, the neglected inferiour people, I entreate, to arme themſelues with patience, conſidering the honour of it; for it argues them nobly ſufficient of themſelues; if they can liue without the fauour, aſwel as the fauour without them, but baſely neceſſitous, if they ſtand in need of it: the profit like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; for what are faces and fauours of Potentate men, but as the face of the Sunne? which many times dryes and withers, &amp; extracts more out of herbs, then euer it did infuſe into them:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2548:4"/>
and I haue euer thought the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were mad vnto the higheſt degree, in quarrelling who ſhould carry the baggage af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Dauid,</hi> as if they had not trouble and taxe enough beſide: &amp; let this perſwade all neglected Counties and Incorporations; ſuffer Potentates with their fauours; beſtow them how they pleaſe; it ſhould neuer cauſe a diuiſion among wiſe men, 'tis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and profit to be without them many times: But you ſay, there are no ſuch, and God be thanked for it; I am very glad to heare the State of our own Kingdome doth ſo well agree with the State of the Kingdome in the Text: for this Text is no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue inferring againſt the preſent ſtate: but a gentle referring of the caution to euery mans conſcience for time to come; <hi>If a Kingdome be vindictiuely diuided againſt it ſelfe:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>and if it be diuided, it can neuer ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What if a <hi>poſitiue</hi> diſhonour? the revenge appeares more iuſt, but the remedy is the ſame: Inferiours, ſuperiours, to bee detreated all; theſe to inflict ſuch gentle puniſhments, as either may not exaſperate great ſpirits to deſire revenge, or els ſuch mighty mortall ſtroakes, as may vtterly diſ-enable them from all power to execute the ſame: for men of vindictiue nature are hard to be reſtrain'd: this was <hi>Gowries</hi> pretence, revenge: ſtop therefore beginnings; for if euer any <hi>Gowrie</hi> diuide, there will neuer want <hi>Alexanders,</hi> and <hi>Logans; Bowers,</hi> and <hi>Sprotts</hi> to take his part: Thoſe on the other, to conſider how much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiu'd they are; propound revenge they doe, and why? <hi>Melle dulcior eſt:</hi> 'tis ſweeter then the hony-combe vnto their ſoules: that's the old pretext, but 'tis an Heathen one: <hi>amicè amicis, inimicè inimicis,</hi> I find it only in <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and among the <hi>Iewes;</hi> but otherwiſe with CHRIST; <hi>Loue your very enemies:</hi> alas, 'tis Satans inſtigation, not their owne: If 't be vniuſt vnto the death it ſelfe, yet hee that's ſo moſt doing now, ſhall ſuffer moſt in th'end: 'Tis a pleaſant damnation to be reveng'd d'ee ſay? Yes, ſo it is to others, but not vnto your ſelues: others indeed delight the combat to ſee you reciprocally pined and waſted, &amp; periſh'd with each others blowes; but you your ſelues, what pleaſure can you take in being made the very fable, the diſeaſe, and ſlaues of other men? <hi>Quid tibi dulcedo ſi non conceditur uti?
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2548:5"/>
Quid tibi, ſi non tibi?</hi> There's no ſuch crime, as is a ſtudied ſinne; there's no ſuch ſtudy to the head, nor paine vnto the heart, as is the torment of revenge: 'Tis honourable to ſuffer &amp; deſpiſe; but to ſeeke revenge, that's a weakneſſe of not being able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure; and that with preiudice to a whole Common-wealth; 'tis Arch-diueliſhly inhumane: I know heerein alſo yee'll ſay, our Kingdome and the Text agree; and GOD be thanked for it; there needes no poſitiue reproofe; but howeuer, a ſuppoſitiue admonition is good againſt time to come; <hi>If a Kingdome bee vindictiuely diuided againſt it ſelfe,</hi> you know what followes, <hi>ſi modo diuidatur, If euer it be diuided it can neuer ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others in the LVCRATIVE kind haue taken paines to generate a faction for money ſake: <hi>Philip</hi> the father of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> beſieges <hi>Olynthus,</hi> could not take it by force, but he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts <hi>Euthicrates</hi> the chiefe Gouernour by money, and ſo he ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues the Countrey betrayed into his hand: ſo much <hi>conetiſme</hi> can doe; and the remedy as before, to entreat all, that ſuch cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumpues may neuer be imployed, either in embaſſie abroad, or in office at home, whereby they ſhal haue any power of ſelling their State-Intelligence for a penſion, their Kingdome for a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den pound: Thoſe of the ſuſpected on the other, to conſider the baſeneſſe of the ſinne, what a thrice-odious earthlineſſe it is to ſell a potent rich Kingdome for a litle red earth: What, the Kingdome? why 'twere much to ſell the virginity of one mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, if ſhe were a pure devoted good creature: but in betraying a Kingdome, the doctrine of Religion, the propagation of Lawes, the orders of Cities, the Arts of Vniuerſities, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of youth, the beauty, maidenhead of Humanity, Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and all they ſell, for a litle handfull of red earth; which when they obtaine, their ſecond generation ſhall neuer carry it to their graue, nor they themſelues be euer buried without an Epitaph of the baſeſt kinde: <hi>Vendidit hic auro patriam;</hi> heere lyes the notorious corrumpue, that ſold his whole Countrey to fill his own cheſt: or that of Saint <hi>Bernard: Viluit huic populi ſalus prae auro Hiſpaniae,</hi> in his 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Booke <hi>de conſid. ad Eugenium.</hi> What cares he, when he is dead? no, nor the Diuell neither; but GOD will make them both care, when he hath them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2548:5"/>
in Hell-fire: Yet ye ſay, there are no ſuch neither, and who is not glad to heare? the State of our owne Kingdome doth ſo well parallell with the Kingdome i'ch' Text: for this is no peremptory reproofe of any preſent State, but a louing aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement againſt time to come: <hi>If a Kingdome be</hi> LVCRATIVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY <hi>diuided againſt it ſelfe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>ſuch a King dome cannot ſtand;</hi> 'tis nothing to our owne: there's the Emphaſis at <hi>that Kingd me,</hi> not our owne: <hi>that Kingdome cannot ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others by being ALLYED to forraine Nations, haue beene inclinable to diuide: as in the <hi>Sicilian</hi> warre, the <hi>Chalcidians</hi> ſaid, they were aunciently allyed to <hi>Athens,</hi> and therefore rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would they ſhould partake with them againſt their owne Kingdome in the warre. 'Tis i'th' 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> booke of <hi>Thucidides,</hi> where you may ſee what the fancie of Allyance can doe in the diuiſion of a State; and the remedy is for Chiefes in any king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to make all their Allyes of marriage and other intereſts of relation, as much as their wiſedome may, among themſelues: and if they chance otherwiſe to be allyed abroad, yet know they muſt, they haue but allyed themſelues to ſuch a priuat fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, to ſuch a publicke Kingdome they cannot allye them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, vnleſſe they'll be Traitours to their owne: to ſuch a Kingdome they cannot allye themſelues, vnleſſe all allye: <hi>Giue vs your daughters to wife,</hi> ſay <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſonnes, <hi>and we will render ye ours:</hi> Let it be a generall allyance, <hi>&amp; erimus quaſi genus unum: Gen. 34.16:</hi> and vnleſſe it be generall, it can be no iuſt tye of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to another State; becauſe the priuate good muſt euer giue preheminence to the publicke weale; they may be defenſiue to another, but neuer offenſiue to their owne: why ſhould they? allyed by wife? but you know not whether it bee your wife or you they doe ſo much reſpect: peradventure others are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed vnto her, as neere as you your ſelues, yet neuer carry opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to ſuch reſpects as thoſe: they reſpect not your kingdome for allyance vnto them; why then ſhould you theirs? If euer the enemy enter, there will be no time to deliberate of Allyes: Pardon the Generall what he pleaſe, yet the Common Souldier will ſlay and rifle what he can: Suppoſe they ſhould offer to exempt yee from the reſt, as <hi>Sylla</hi> did ſome ſpeciall friends of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2548:6"/>
his, when <hi>Praeneſte</hi> was beſieged, yet were ye noble ſpirits, yee would ſcorne to accept the condition, ye would ruſh in among the troopes, and chooſe rather to die for the honour of your Country, as thoſe <hi>Praeneſtians</hi> did: But I heare you ſay, you feare no ſuch <hi>Allyes</hi> neither, and I am glad yee are ſo paralell in all things with the Text, which hath no abſolute reproofe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but only admonition againſt time to come; <hi>If a Kingdome be</hi> MATRIMONIALLY <hi>diuided againſt itſelfe, that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome cannot ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet giue me leaue, what ſay ye to <hi>Alliance in Religion,</hi> which is the grand of all? for <hi>diuiſion in Religion</hi> ſets Preacher againſt Preacher; one Oratour, one Lecturer againſt another; diuiſion in Religion ſetts Scribe againſt Scribe; one Hearer, one Reader againſt another; diuiſion in Religion ſets Prince and People, Nobles and Gentry, Clergie and Commonalty, euery man, and all together by the faces: the very name of Religion bearing ſhew of honour in the profeſſion, of merit in the defence, makes many moſt willing to dye for their Religion, if it be but <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio vitulorum,</hi> the Religion of Calues and Images, yet you know they'll ſuffer death for their Religion: if you know it not, yet <hi>Ieroboam</hi> did, and that made him allye the tenne Tribes to another Religion then that of <hi>Iudah,</hi> aſſuring himſelfe they would not very ſoone complye with <hi>Iudah</hi> againe: ſo much <hi>diuiſion of Religion can doe;</hi> and what ſhall we ſay? that heerein alſo we are paralell to the Text? certainely, either are, or may be very eaſily by redreſſe: Let the order of Miniſters be the ſame, Oath of Allegiance the ſame; diuine ſeruice all the ſame; articles of Beleefe, number of Sacraments, authority of Scripture throughout the whole Kingdome the ſame, and let it be paine of death to him that will tranſgreſſe, if he practiſe others but with a ſpeaking countenance to doe the like: ſo ſhall we ſoone be paralell to the Text: for if their idolatrous Prieſts be baniſht, who ſhall ſweare their Children to diſobey the Crowne? who ſhall marry them when they come to yeares? or what lawfull iſſue ſhall they haue, if they be not married as they ought? I ſpeake it with a <hi>Deo gratias</hi> from my heart, you haue a Law, then which there cannot bee deuiſed a more prudent, a more
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2548:6"/>
Chriſtian, no not a more taking way to reduce the Religion of a Kingdome all to one: onely let it haue due execution; he is not <hi>Caeſars</hi> nor the Kingdomes friend, that will not zealouſly execute that Law, <hi>after the diuided haue beene beſought</hi> to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the difference betweene our diuiner ſolace, and their poore Romane ioy? we pronounce full abſolution from Hell &amp; Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and all other ſecret torments whatſoeuer are vnknown to mortall man, facilitating their laſt paſſage with ſweetneſſe of the greateſt hope, whereas they leaue the moſt in feare of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, and many times in ſuſpence of Hell it ſelfe: and is there no difference of gladneſſe? wee apply free remiſſion while they are aliue; they make them pay for it after they are dead; and is there no difference in the profit then? we carry them like noble men vnto the Table of the greateſt King, in the comely geſture of fellow-heires with CHRIST; but they make them creep like ſlaues vnto it: wee vnfoulding the whole Volume of GODS Word, make them fellow-Iudges of other mens liues, and of their doctrine too: but they leade them blind-fold vnto Hell: wee make them partakers both of Bread and Wine; they giue them only dry bread at the Communion Table, and is there no difference in the honour then? We tranſlate the Bible for them to ſerue GOD in a well-knowne tongue; but they impoſe a language, which the people doth not vnderſtand; and is there no difference of difficulty then? thus you may detreate them peraduenture without execution of the Law: but who? The Clergy dare not approach vnto them without feare of poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or that which is worſe: Plebeïans haue no power among them: great ones therfore, euery man according to his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, his conſanguinitie, his any reſpect whatſoeuer ſhould aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay (the vtmoſt he could) to haue them all allyed in the ſame Religion with vs. O that <hi>Solomon</hi> or his Courtiers had bin ſo induſtrious to wooe and winne the ſoules of idolatrous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as they were their bodies to command, ſoone would the women haue ſided in the ſame Religion with them, and aſſoone their Prieſts bin gone: though 'twere harſh at firſt, yet to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity very gratefull would it be, and many thankes would they ſurrender for it: thus wrought vpon; thus allyed in th'unity of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2548:7"/>
the ſame Religion might they be: by Euangelicall perſwaſions in priuate, by legall executions in publicke: Tis no Religion to abſtaine from diuiſion your ſelues, vnleſſe yee endeauour to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh it in others alſo; that's true Religion indeed, ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtine; parum eſt non excitare, niſi etiam extinguere coneris:</hi> There's no ſuch excuſe for tollerating two Religions in our Kingdome, as there is in ſome <hi>Lutherane</hi> Churches: for they are in perill of deſolation, if not; but wee (God be praiſed) in a ſafer caſe: wherefore if yee'll doe nothing els, yet let the royall Statutes haue their force; and then heerein alſo wee ſhall bee quickly equal to the Text, we ſhall not need any fierce reproof, only a gentle caution againſt time to come; beware of <hi>diuiſion in Religion</hi> aboue all; for <hi>if a Kingdome be</hi> MISRELIGIOVSLY <hi>diuided againſt it ſelfe, that Kingdome of all others can neuer long ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Will you haue higher then theſe? the Poëts moralize <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> for chaſtizing his father <hi>Coelum; caſtravit patrem;</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> for depoſing <hi>Saturne;</hi> and the naturall cauſes, (the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks ſay) for depoſing <hi>Iupiter:</hi> The ſubſtance is, <hi>Caracalla</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed againſt <hi>Severus,</hi> and <hi>Abſalom</hi> againſt <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> the ſonne againſt the father, or one Princely brother a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another: This is the higheſt diuiſion, and the remedy as before; to beſeech euery ſoueraigne father, hee would not ſtreighten his ſonnes too much in looſing them the flower of their age: rather reſigne ſome portion of his Kingdome, honors or offices before death, whereon to exerciſe the power of his regall skill; as <hi>Dauid</hi> did the whole to <hi>Solomon, 1 Chron. 23.1:</hi> and if he haue moe ſonnes then lawfull wiues or kingdomes to poſſeſſe, then to compoſe the matter prudently before, leſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the kingdome ſuffer a diuiſion by it; as't did in <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaloms</hi> time, one halfe cleauing to the father, the other accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicing with the ſonne, wherein <hi>Abſalom</hi> was chiefe offendour, yet <hi>Dauid</hi> not altogether without ſinne: on th'other part thoſe royall branches ſhould conſider the thornes that be annext vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Crowne: O did a Prince apparent know, what ſlauiſh deadly troubles, what perils of poiſons, what treaſons are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto; what bloudie iudgments, what hell it ſelfe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2548:7"/>
eſpecially if it bee not very rightly his; then would hee ſoone throw downe himſelfe, his Crowne &amp; all, to adore ſuch a peece of earth with a moſt religious kiſſe, as would but vnburthen him of ſo great a paine: as 'twas moſt elegantly aduertiſ'd by our fourth King <hi>Harry</hi> to his ſonne: But heerein aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yee may moſt iuſtly ſay, our Kingdome is agreeable to the Text, there needes no preſent rebuke for <hi>ſuch ambitious diuiſion,</hi> onely a gentle admonition is good againſt time to come, <hi>If a kingdome be ſo</hi> CAPITALLY <hi>divided againſt it ſelfe, that kingdome can neuer ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What more? Sometimes the diuiſion ariſeth meerely from the harſhneſſe of a King, as when <hi>Alexander</hi> paſt ouer himſelfe and all his fauours by deed-of-gift into the <hi>Perſian</hi> habite; ſo reprobating the very hopes of all his natiue <hi>Macedons</hi> at one acte: or as when <hi>Rehoboam</hi> with one proud tyrannicall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, turn'd ten great Tribes into ſo many traytors at a breath: certainely the remedy is for Kings to forbeare ſuch needleſſe provocations, but Subiects them to beare: what if once in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen generations come <hi>Rehoboams</hi> courſe to weare the Crowne? yet 'tis no warrant for Subiects to play the Traytours becauſe their Soueraigne playes the folly: What if once in ſeauen gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations? what's that to vs? yet 'tis not ſo, nor likely to bee ſo in our time: therefore there needes no reproofe heere neither, but howeuer a gentle remembrance is good againſt time to come: <hi>If a Kingdome be</hi> TYRANNICALLY <hi>diuided againſt it ſelfe, that Kingdome can neuer ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are <hi>provocations within,</hi> there are <hi>inſtigations with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,</hi> as the <hi>Syracuſan</hi> Oratour taught the <hi>Camarins</hi> touching their neighbour <hi>Athenians,</hi> that they ſhould beware them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did wholly apply themſelues to worke diſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diuiſions in other mens Kingdomes; <hi>ut alios ab alijs diſſociarent:</hi> ſo I am afraid doe ſome neighbour-Nations vpon vs, as well as others: I would to God 'twere otherwiſe, and that heerein alſo we were equall to the Text: but there are ſtrong preſumptions to the contrary: <hi>Pompeius Trogus</hi> an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Hiſtorian ſayes, there is a Kingdome neere vs of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet minde, their weapons dearer then their bloud vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2548:8"/>
women adminiſter tillage to what they haue already, but they ſeeke abroad for more: of an vnquiet minde? and ſeek abroad for more? Heere's preſumption enough: can there bee two greater incendiaries then Polupragmacy and auarice? vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe of minde, and covetouſneſſe of goods? any one of them if it be well followed, <hi>doctis dolis,</hi> haue a learned <hi>diſſimulador</hi> for an Agent, 'tis enough to diuide all the Kingdomes in the World, it is: what Kingdome is there, wherein you ſhall not finde a Polupragmatiſt, one or other? an <hi>Antony</hi> that will make the warre vpon <hi>Octavius,</hi> be it neuer ſo vniuſt: alas this <hi>Inquietudo naturae,</hi> 'tis but his nature, he cannot bee quiet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he doe diuide: and when two ſuch meet together, 'tis like the meeting of two windes, and what doe they make but a whirle-winde? and what does the whirle-winde (ſayes the Philoſopher) but gather a company of leaues and feathers to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? and what's that company, but one part of the diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? What ſpeake I of vnquietnes by nature? there is an vnſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ambition of domineering ouer all: What meane thoſe vulgar reports, that they can diuide the Commons and the King, and ſo by a tollerable kinde of treaſon blow vp a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament without gun-powder, when euer they pleaſe? What mean thoſe complaints from beyond the Seas, that their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes haue bin diuided from them? yet all this I know would ſeeme fabulous to ſome, did not their more then too much audaciouſneſſe ſo lately refreſh the verity of it, whenas in the face of the whole Realme they attempted a diuiſion between the Kinglie Father and the Princely Sonne: what? attempt a diuiſion betweene the Trinity? Tis only that is greater then this? now woe vpon ſuch diuels incarnate, ſuch forges, ſuch fire-brands, ſuch bellowes, ſuch very windes of Hell! neuer ceaſe coueting of other mens Valtolines? O ſay the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, if they were once altogether in that Valtoline, where they might couet a droppe of Engliſh water to coole their tongues, then they would ſurceaſe: ſtill making diviſions by their mineralls amongſt vs? If they were once in that diuiſion of places among the ſulphures and the mineralls, from whence there is no redemption; where the fire diuides betweene the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2548:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ioynts &amp; the marrow; there they ſhould haue diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enough; their fill: —Good ye vnerring Iewry remember theſe when yee come to fit vpon the twelue Tribes; what compound ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners! ambitious, vniuſt, intemperate, vnnameable tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours! cenſure them deepe enough: but can the malignant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Planets &amp; blazing ſtarres do nothing i'th' mean time? Thou that ruleſt from the ſupreameſt or be to the center of the earth, ſhall ſuch a kingdome ſtand, as ſeekes the ruinous diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all other Chriſtian kingdomes in the world, and that at ſuch a time, as they ſtand in greateſt need to combine al againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon aduerſary of Chriſt? They would cut all thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts throats: they would burne all the profeſſours of thy trueth: they would toſſe, they would teare thy deareſt childrens ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der limbes on cold hearted iron ſpeares: they would crucifie them beyond eternity, if they could. All theſe things haſt thou ſeene! But when? did euer our agents ſeek to make a diuiſion in their ſtate? or their owne beſt authors legitimate their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it in ours? Stratagems in time of warre, ſollicitations to rebell, then peraduenture lawfull in ſome caſe; but when in peace, in time of league waſt euer heard? ſpeake thou that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ind'ſt <hi>Iehoiakim</hi> for not keeping his faith with an heathen king, ith <hi>2. of K. 24. chap</hi> and when thou ſpeakſt reuenge thy ſelfe, not vs, thy deare Apoſtolicall truth: thou that haſt numbred <hi>hatred and variance, ſtrifes and ſedition, ith' 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the Galat. among ſuch operations as ſhall neuer inherit euerlaſting life: thou that hateſt ſix things and accounteſt the ſeauenth a very abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to thy ſoule, Prov. 6.16. a prowd looke, a lying tongue, bloudy hands ſwift feet</hi> (from Indies to Indies) <hi>and that ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth diſcord among brethren;</hi> are they not all in them? for when they are amongſt vs, they take ſeaſon, and they ſowe, and they ſowe diſcord, and that which is the moſt abſtract abomination of all, they ſowe diſcord among brethren; among naturall, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſpirituall brethren, nay betweene the ſubiect &amp; the king betweene father and ſonne they ſowe it: If Scripture moue not, what ſaies their owne <hi>Secunda 2 ae</hi> in his 37<hi rend="sup">th</hi> queſtion? that is at diſcord ſinnes, but that introduceth diſcord is a greater ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and therefore the greater damnation he ſhall receaue. But
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2548:9"/>
returne to Scripture againe, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> did induce diſcord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the <hi>Sadduces</hi> and the <hi>Phariſees. Acts 23.</hi> but returne to expoſition againe and their owne authors ſhall condemne them; for <hi>Aquinas</hi> forecited ſaies, and <hi>Caietan</hi> vpon <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaies, and <hi>Lorinus</hi> the man whom they all reuerence ſaies, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> did not purpoſely intend it, but accidentally procure it to be done: or if purpoſely; yet 'twas an euill hereticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, not a good correſpondency the Apoſtle did diuide: or if a good concord he did diuide, yet he did it by true allegations, not by falſe; or if by falſe allegations; yet 'twas with open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of diſtaſt, not vnder colour of goodwill: whereas they doe it of ſtudied purpoſe, to diuide the beſt concord, and that by moſt diueliſh falſe detractions, and that vnder profeſſion of peace and league they doe it: theres the height, but where's the remedy? vnleſſe as before, to entreat others Highneſſe, lownes, all: Thoſe that they <hi>ſuffer no ſuch nation (whoſoeuer it be) to hold any farther knowledge or correspondency in our kingdome, then they can take by force of armes:</hi> 'twas the counſell of <hi>Don Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardino</hi> to <hi>Philip</hi> Prince of <hi>Caſtile:</hi> theſe that they giue no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther credit to their accuſations againſt one or other, then God himſelfe did, when the Diuell accuſed <hi>Iob: ad mutuam diffiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam inducere</hi> (faith <hi>Thucidides</hi>) there's nothing ſtrengthens the enimy more, then for people to diſtruſt each other: nothing ſtrengthens a people more then to diſtruſt the enimy: therefore beleeue them no farther, then the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> did <hi>Achiſh,</hi> 1 Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, 29.3. Where they ſtill cryed out: <hi>What doe the Hebrews here amongſt vs?</hi> So long as they are enimies, there's no other pleading, but <hi>quid hic Hebraei?</hi> Why not we as wiſe in our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, as they in theirs: <hi>Imò quid hic Romani?</hi> What doe our mortall enimies the <hi>Romans</hi> here amongſt vs? If they'll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, wee'll accompany them to the ſhoare; that was euer the wiſdome of the ancient, leaſt by communication of language, they ſhould corrupt the people, ſayes the hiſtorian: <hi>per commer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium linguae:</hi> if not depart, yet bridle them <hi>from speaking into the common peoples eares, as Eliakim beſought Rabſekah, 2 K. 18 to eſtrange his language, leaſt the people ſhould revolt:</hi> If none of theſe, but that they will remaine, and will make diuiſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2548:9"/>
vs; let euery plot haue his counter-plot, as the <hi>Plata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſerued the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> let them haue diuiſion for diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let their bowels be diuided in the midſt: <hi>nec lex eſt aequior vlla:</hi> or if that too ſeuere, yet let their tongues be diuided in the midſt: the affinity of the puniſhment doth ſo aptly reſemble the ſinne; neuer would nation more be guilty of ſuch crime, as whoſe mocking puniſhment ſhould bee ſo wittily the accuſer of it ſelfe. Something muſt be done, and the ſafeſt is to keepe them out with iron haileſtones, <hi>grandine ferreo,</hi> as that Queene of heauen did after 88: Neuer kingdome ſo wel ſtated, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents would ariſe through naughty adminiſtration of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, partialities in choice of officers, one way or other; if peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple refraine their appetites, yet alwaies not a Prince; if a Prince refraine his paſſions, yet alwaies not a people. 'Tis to be noted, ſaith <hi>Bernardino,</hi> in this matter of malecontents, that they are to be found in all kingdomes, Prouinces, and the very Courts of Princes themſelues, yee may finde men to worke vpon. It being annext to humane nature, that men are neuer ſatisfied, no not with the gouerments, which our Lord God himſelfe ordaines: no maruell then if they be diſcontented with the rules of more ordinary kings; ſuch is the corruption of vniuerſall nature, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to imagine he could gouerne better, then the man who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hee bee that is in place. Theſe are the humours to bee wrought vpon: Say they ſo? Therefore ſomething of neceſſity muſt be done ſhall I ſay? Nay therefore many things are done by men of potentate place: the <hi>Firebrands</hi> are remoued; the <hi>prouoking cauſe</hi> is taken away, all that were <hi>giuen to incenſe</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion are now reſtrain'd; there needs no poſitiue reproofe, for herein alſo are we equall to the Text; yet a cautelous admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is good againſt time to come: <hi>If a kingdome doe admit ſuch ſtirrers of diuiſions to reſide among them, that kingdome neuer long can ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Howſoeuer our owne preſent care muſt bee, that wee our ſelues belong not to the number of thoſe that will by any meanes <hi>be prouoked</hi> to ſuch a ſinne. 'Tis all th'aduerſary deſires in any ſtate, to finde ſuch matter to worke vpon: 'tis their open profeſſion, to fiſh in troubled waters: If you'l be tinder, they'll
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2548:10"/>
be Fire: If you'l be Waues, thei'l be quickly Winds: If you'l be diſcontented, thei'l quickly ſeduce yee to diuide: If you'l float, thei'l quickly contriue yee to their owne ſide: Wherefore I beſeech yee receaue a gentle perſuaſiue remedie for this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe alſo: what doe's the vnfortunately neceſſitous conceaue? That his caſe is deſperate? Or what the prodigall waſter of his ſubſtance? that he cannot ſatisfie by making payment of the debt? What then? Can hee therefore ſatisfie by making a diuiſion in the land? Will one ſinne expiate another? No more then one puniſhment will eaſe another: better therefore hee fall into the Creditours hands alone, then into the diuells too, where he ſhall be ſure to pay the vtmoſt farthing for both, &amp; yet neuer ſhall come forth: Or what th'ambitious male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent? That hee is not officed according to his worth? What then? that's anothers default, 'tis none of his: but if hee make a diuiſion vpon it, then the ſinne is his owne, and then hee may quickly be officed according to his worth: Are vnworthies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted? Stomacke it he may; declare it ſeaſonably to preſidents of ſtate he may; but make a diuiſion for it among the multitude that he may not: 'twere a moſt fooliſh indiſcretion, and more then a deadly ſin: Or what the vaineglorious diſcontent, whoſe ſelfe-loue will neuer be ſatisfied, what attributes ſoeuer yee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon him; vnleſſe that Country, that Shire, and that very part of the ſhiere, wherein he was borne bee prefer'd before all other Countries and kingdomes ith' world beſide: vnleſſe that booke, that methode, and that expoſition which he likes, be deified before all other methods and expoſitions that are; vnleſſe that ranke, that condition whereto he belongs be mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified aboue all other rankes and conditions whatſoeere they be. Thus they ſet <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Northerne &amp; Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne at variance among themſelues. Thus they make Nobles to deſpize Commons, and Commons to diſtaſt Nobles, and King and Clergy to be diuided from them both: Are theſe the ingenuous men yee ſpeake off? Now I beſeech them, what Poet or Orator, what Hiſtorian or Diuine did euer teach them this wit to diuide a powerable kingdom againt it ſelfe? Were there any depth of wiſdome in them, they would neuer deſire
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2548:10"/>
all of their ſhire, all of their condition to bee ſo highly extold aboue the reſt: becauſe then there is no excellency left for him: If all be ſuch, where I pray is the difference of <hi>acumen</hi> that is belonging vnto him? All theſe are fit materials for a diuiſion. Their conferences, newes, letters, verſes, ſpeeches, Sermous, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting of nothing more, then of deſire to diuide; whereat the enimy doth much reioyce, and hopes to ſucke no ſmall aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage out of ſuch diuiſions ith'end. Wherefore they are often to be entreated, that they would abandon all diſcontent, leaue off ſuch fooliſh factious words, partake with neither ſide to the preiudice of the whole; but in a loueable prudent kinde render to euery place his due; affection to whom affection, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to whom ſubiection is due, yet ſtill keeping the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency of the whole together; not ſo ſubiect to a King as to talke <hi>tyranny</hi> againſt a ſtate, nor ſo affected to a ſtate as to ſpeake <hi>treaſon</hi> againſt a king: not ſo partake with Nobles as to <hi>oppreſſe</hi> the Commons, nor ſo with Commons as to <hi>ſcandall</hi> Nobles: not ſo with Citty, as to incenſe the Country, nor ſo with Country as to enrage the Citty: not they vilifie our Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie to magnifie their Laitee, nor we vilifie their Laitee, to dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie our Clergie; becauſe all theſe are the beginnings of diuiſion: but euery man being humble in his owne eyes, let him eſteeme another better then himſelfe, &amp; the preſeruation of the whole to be greater then all; ſo ſhall we be all free from the greatnes of this nationall ſinne, <hi>The diuiſion of a land.</hi> If any be otherwiſe minded, and will maintaine a faction ſtill, that <hi>Man-diuell</hi> is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Caeſars</hi> nor the kingdomes friend: for he doth but prepare the <hi>Fuell</hi> of diuiſion to th'aduerſaries hand; be doth but main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch engins, as when any ſubtle plot-maſter meets with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that kingdome can neuer long ſtand. Some of them the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate may meet withall: if their number gather head and troupe together, yee knowe the remedie is in the law: yee haue priſons for wandring rogues; houſes of correction for idle tongu'd parties, miſteries of trades for indigent men of occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation: let the multitude be looked vnto, and each man enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in his owne proper place: 'tis alwaies beſt walking in the ſafeſt way. The hitory of <hi>Florence</hi> can report vnt'ce, what
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2548:11"/>
inſolent diuiſions haue ariſen from certaine diſtaſts about the my ſteries of wooll. The hiſtory of the <hi>Turks,</hi> what armies haue growne from exiles &amp; malecontents. The hiſtory of the <hi>Kings</hi> inſteed of al; <hi>Euery one that was in diſtreſſe, euery one that was in debt, and euery one that was diſcontented gathered themſelues to Dauid, and hee became a Captaine ouer them:</hi> ſaies the Text, <hi>1. Sam. 22.2</hi> Theſe things yee knowe: happy are yee if yee doe them: as ſuperiours haue done their part, ſo let vs doe ours; they haue taken the FIRE away: let vs remoue the FVELL too. <hi>For if a Kingdome retaine but the fit fuell of diuiſion within it ſeife, that kingdome can neuer long ſtand</hi>—So ye haue corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions within, prouocations without, and the <hi>particular reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> of both. Two other more <hi>generall remedies</hi> there are, <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and Prayer.</hi> Conſider how VNPLEASANT it is to nouriſh a diuiſion in any kinde: whether you ſit at your dayly meales, walke in the priuat recreations of your gardens, or hold a parly in any other perambulations that yee make, come there a pleaſant conceit into your head, you dare not vtter it; come there a lofty cenſure, you dare not vtter it; for feare of miſpriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, miſinterpretation, condemnation, you dare not vtter any thing: write any thing, it ſhall be cenſur'd; ſay any thing, it ſhall be cenſur'd; nay thinke any thing, or if you pleaſe thinke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, yet will they cenſure the very <hi>non-imaginations</hi> of your thoughts: ô what a life is this? you haue a preſident of it at Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus; <hi>Thucidides</hi> ſets it forth by three as vnpleaſant things as euer mortalitie did endure, ſuſpition, ſilence, death: a hurly burly; euery man ſuſpected his deareſt friend, and in that ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion kept ſilence in the deepe of his heart; but—paine and griefe vnto them; and that which was the plague of all, their ſilence was their death, becauſe they durſt not anſwer of what faction they did partake: yee gentle ſweet diſpoſitions of amitie and peace, who would not hate, abhorre the authors of diuiſions? diſturbers of all your Chriſtian quiet, troublers of your hearts, impeachers of all your ioy; that Chriſtian liberty, that ſweetnes of conuerſation, that honeſt cheerefulneſſe, that tranquility of body and minde, wherein God allowes euery man to paſſe his time away; how doe they hinder all? O had you euer liued in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2548:11"/>
houſe or kingdome where diuiſions are, you wold ſay it were a certaine kinde of hell to be depriued of that ſollace, which in peaceable louing ſocieties yee might enioy. Stand ye newtrall, partake neither ſide, yet will the one ſtrangle yee with ſmoake, the other ſlander yee with baſer kitchinſtuffe, ſaies <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> yee were as good dwell in the middle chamber of an houſe, which is ſure to be abuſed of either ſide: but if yee bee farther intereſted to beare a part in the ſtudy of reuenge, how vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a torment is it then vnto the braine, heart, &amp; ſoule of man? what plodding, plotting, carking, caring, contriuing muſt there be? A man were better vphold the building of 9 ſeuerall houſes with his ſhoulders; then beare vp the burden of one ſuch diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with his head. Therefore for the odious vnpleaſantneſſe of it let all men avoid this ſinne of diuiſion: for the very ſorrow &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content thereof is enough to kill the greateſt, goodeſt part of men: <hi>If a kingdome be diuided againſt it ſelfe, it can neuer ſtand in temper long, for very ſorrow that it cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who would not couer his face with a ſhamefull bluſh, to be the author of ſo many <hi>vncomely</hi> diſorders in a ſtate? Bring in a diuiſion once, &amp; yee diſrobe the kingdome of all gracefull mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings whatſoeuer they be: no ſuch Acts of Parliament; no ſuch Commencements i'ch' Vniuerſitie, no ſuch feſtiualls of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try pompe, no ſuch ſolemne celebrations at the Court; no ſuch aſſemblies of ſcarlet at the market, no ſuch glorious congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Diuines at Churches, as now adaies there are. Bring in a diuiſion, yee ſet ſonne againſt father, ſeruant againſt maſter, the vaſſall againſt the king himſelfe: what irreuerent geſtures, vnſeemly words, ſawere actions? <hi>Alexander</hi> flies into the kings royall face, graſps him by the tender ſoft throat, thruſts two or three of his homelieſt reprobate fingers into the Kings ſweet eloquent mouth, to ſtop the paſſage, that hee might neither call on God nor man for ſuccour. So and no otherwiſe will your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriours ſerue you all: euery ſtrong handed baſer fellowe will kicke yee, and teare yee, and trample yee, &amp; all the good report yee haue into vtter reproach, if euer yee introduce a diuiſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtate: no beauty of body, no good friendſhip of mind, no good report abroad, no contentment at home, no true felicity
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2548:12"/>
of any kinde can yee ſecure vnto your ſelues, if euer ye bring a diuiſion into the land; whoſe heart then is not fill'd with holy indignation againſt ſuch as are the authors of diuiſion? that one illfauor'd fellow ſhould vndoe ſo many rare comely beauties: one baſe newter vndoe ſo many true loyall hearts! What? take away the forme &amp; beautie of our kingdom fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs? 'tis all one, as if they ſhould confuſe the order of the ſtats; or take the ſpring from our the glorie of the yeare: for ſhame of diſhonour then doe not a diuiſion breed: if a kingdome bee diuided againſt it ſelſe, it can neuer ſtand long in the excellency of its former glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that it cannot: and then as good it neuer ſtood at all: <hi>If a kingdome be diuided againſt it ſelfe, that kingdom can neuer ſtand in any good faſhion as it ought to doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I ſhould open the DISPROFITS of it; how it embaſeth and impoueriſheth the whole common-wealth:-traffickes of wine, trafficks of rarer merchandiſe, it is diuiſion ſets the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter impoſt on them: dealings in Cartle, tradings in cloath, it is diviſion ſets the greater price vpon them: it is diuiſion many times that makes the price of corne to riſe: It is diuiſion of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitours that makes the Landlord ſtate his farmage at ſo high a rate: Tis diuiſion makes Gold and Iewells to be exported in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other lands: 'tis diuiſion makes each man betray his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour into the enimies hands; to the Pyrat; to the robber, the murtherer; what not? And I wonder the authors of it doe not foreſee, that it will be ith'end as preiudiciall to themſelues as others; for the ruine of particulars will proue the ruine of the vniuerſall in the end, and a wiſe Counſellour did long agoe aduertiſe the <hi>Sicilian</hi> ſtate.</p>
            <p>Beſides other <hi>dangers,</hi> which are poſſible enough: for whom will you call in to decide the cauſe, if a diuiſion ſhould ariſe? I will only enforme yee what I haue read touching <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> reputed a man of clemencie, yet when euer he was called in to be a Iudge of differences in any kingdome, hee did alwaies (not <hi>Venire</hi> but) <hi>ſupervenire,</hi> ſaies the Text, <hi>ad iudicium tanquam ad bellum:</hi> he came vpon them alwaies with an Armie ready furniſht, and I beſeech you marke the euent, for ſo he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd the Empire from them both: 'tis ith' 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> booke of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2548:12"/>
Sic vtrun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> regno ſpoliauit:</hi> And are there now none as greedy after other mens kingdomes, as euer <hi>Philip</hi> was? I would it were not too well knowne, that thoſe which are the right <hi>male Catolici</hi> indeed doe acknowledge another Catholike king in temporalls to be aboue our Soueraigne, as well as the Pope in Spiritualls to be aboue our Archbiſhop: and is not this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous? Who knowes not how conſtant <hi>Flanders</hi> was to the kingdome of <hi>France,</hi> till a great miſleader perſwaded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there was another King of <hi>France</hi> beſide <hi>Philip?</hi> then preſently they reuolted from him: and to ſpeake all, the <hi>Grecian</hi> Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were in an vproare, for want of expreſſion to their joy, and thought they had accuſation enough againſt the Apoſtles, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they found them teaching, <hi>there was another King beſide Caeſar, Act. 17.7</hi> and for certaine it had beene a dangerous doctrine, if of a temporall King: as yee'll take them teaching it of a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall King, that there is another Soueraigne beſide our <hi>Caeſar:</hi> wherefore be not miſcarried to their bed of ſleepe: yee knowe the diſprofit, yee knowe the danger of it: ſuppoſe the enemy were approaching to the walls: the Citty arme themſelues; the valiant men of warre marching forward with greater fury then the reſt, encounter the enimy at the gates; and now they charge and then looke backe againe; and now they fight, and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine looke backe, for feare their greateſt enimies bee behinde them, a diuiſion of their own: yet ſtill they make good the wall, vntil the heat of skirmiſh be began, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the miſtery of diſcord alſo begins to worke, and here a Captaine flags, and there ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther falſifies his fire: and one man ſhoots the enimy; &amp; another ſhoots his fellow Cittizen that is next vnto him; thus the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion workes: and then to handy ſtroakes they come amongſt themſelues: the throat that's next him then, each bloudy blade bereaues him of his life: then their glittering ſwords are ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed into each others guts: the hewing Axe and wounding Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronell ſet bloud for bloud abroach: no matter though the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie doe preuaile, ſaith the diſſentious man, yet howſoeuer this villaine my neighbour ſhall neuer liue to triumph ouer me againe, and downe he beates him to the ground: thus each butchers other, while the enimie is glad to enter on ſo rich a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2548:13"/>
ſpoile: and thus a Citty and thus a kingdome is too too often loſt: whereas if they were vnanimous among themſelues, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimy might ſacrifice his powder to the empty ayre; and feed vpon the ſound thereof inſteed of richer ſpoiles. Alas, ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, The children of mine own mother, mine owne mothers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren haue fought againſt me,</hi> no marvell if I fall.—If thus you ſtand affected againſt each other; Alas the fruſtrate enterpriſes of our former Queene! Alas the fayling hopes of peaceable men! the too much deceaued expectation of vs all: for I ſee you fighting, weeping, bleeding, dying; ſtanding wet-ſhoo'd vp to the very ankles in each others bloud, and more fearefully then ſo, 'tis deepe blood, 'tis very dreadfull goarebloud I ſee; if ſo! I ſay; if ſo! For I delight not theſe heauy deſcriptions, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diuine happy things vnt'ee: yet weigh well the danger, thats the beſt preuenting way: knowe yee not that the furious Diuell walks his rounds? the whole world is his family at hand and becke: <hi>non infans vnius diei, imo non infans vnius Dei:</hi> not an infant of a day old, but he labours to make it child of wrath, and of diuiſion as well as others.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tu potes vnanimes armare in Praelia fratres,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>tibi nominae mille—mille nocendi artes:</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
A thouſand ſeuerall arts he hath to make diuiſion in a land, hee hath falſe teachers of euery kinde, &amp; varieties of furies at com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: the world full of ambition without; we of vnconſtancy within: each gaping after change. Tis no age for <hi>Tacitus</hi> his Prince to commit neighbour Prouinces againſt each other: that's when he feares a conſpiracy within, but we moſt without: they are all growne <hi>Machiavellians</hi> now: <hi>diuide &amp; impera;</hi> tis the precept, the practiſe of them all: ſafe for them; dangerous for vs: if none of theſe will moue; goe then yee Pilot-marriners and make yee a tumult in the ſhip, let the windes blow, and the ſurging waues arife, and the enimy come vpon yee, yet ſtill be yee roaring mad againſt each other; there is no feare of robbing drowning, dying; there is no danger in it: Alas, yes; nothing more; vnleſſe yee ſtand conſtant to the whole, vnanimouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to each other, with one heart and hand to liue and dy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; there's no preſervation neither of ſhippe nor kingdome,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2548:13"/>
that there is not: vnleſſe yee bee all like <hi>Neſtor</hi> and <hi>Achilles,</hi> whom neither Court nor Country did euer heare to iarre. Fly therefore faction, renounce debate; ſharpe is the enimies ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke ſet with choller of ambition and reuenge: why will yee gratifie the <hi>Roman</hi> power by committing your tongues, your ſwords one againſt another? neuer talke againſt diuiſion, but liue againſt it: neuer ſay peace, peace; but doe it: <hi>pacatiùs loque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, quàm vivis:</hi> put vp your two-edg'd wordes into their ſheaths: leaue off inuectiue Sermons; and each intemperate, bloody, good name-killing abuſe: each man bee reconciled to his foe: great <hi>Babylon</hi> it ſelfe can neuer ſtand, if <hi>Euphrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into three hundred ſluces, as 'twas in <hi>Cyrus</hi> time: put le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall remedies in execution, and by all euengelicall ſweetneſſe let vs ſtudy to preſerue the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peace: one law, one religion, one King, and one kingdome let vs by; yee all mioy the ſame ayre, which makes your complexions to bee liker to each other, then yee are to any other kingdome in the world beſide: yee all partake the ſame bloud by interveining marriages with each other: yee all partake the ſame diet, the ſame ſtudies; the ſame tutelary Angells doe defend yee all: why ſhould there be any diuiſion amongſt yee? becauſe yee hate to be reconciled? But <hi>Diuiſion will reconcile yee, whether yee will or no:</hi> See the ſhallowneſſe: for diuiſion at home doth euer call in ſome warlike nation from abroad, and they will make you <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici inimicis, &amp; inimici amicis;</hi> friends with your vtter'ſt eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which would make a wiſe man mad; and I would to God it would make mad men wiſe alſo, for it will make you enimies with your beſt friends too, whether you will or no; as the wiſe <hi>Hermocrates</hi> did eaſily fore ſee: <hi>ſo</hi> that if neither for diſpleaſure, nor diſhonour, nor diſprofir, nor danger neither, yet <hi>for neceſſity</hi> it ſelfe each man of prudence diuiſion ſhould avoid.</p>
            <p>What higher? but their <hi>executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here, &amp; the tormentiue puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of hell hereafter:</hi> Read <hi>Suidas,</hi> pervſe the <hi>Athenian,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Commonwealth; they were euer baniſht or impriſond, or put to more ſhamefull deaths. Remember <hi>Phryno, Philocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Theagenes,</hi> &amp; the reſt: eſcape the common Souldiers know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, yet the magiſtracy found meanes againſt them: eſcape
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2548:14"/>
the magiſtracy, yet the Commous drew them to the market place, cut off their hands and bad them goe now &amp; diuide more kingdomes, betray more Citties, if they could: eſcape both Commons &amp; Magiſtracie; yet can they neuer eſcape the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: that diuides a man is murtherer of one; that a pregnant woman of more then that a man; and that a Church of more then that a woman: but hee that a kingdome doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide, is a greater ſinner then them all: hee deſtroies truth, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, chaſtity, religion, from mothers, from Churches, elect, and reprobate altogether: this is more then parricide, or tyrant, or the diuell himſelfe did euer doe: the ſinne of a whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the ſorrowes of a whole kingdome are his guilt; &amp; therefore his doome, as much as the puniſhment of a whole kingdome ſhall it be: ô did ſuch a <hi>diuiſioner</hi> ſee, what an intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable ſumme they make, when they come altogether: put <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſſes</hi> puniſhment to <hi>Iudaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Iudaſſes</hi> to <hi>Ahabs,</hi> and <hi>Ahabt</hi> to <hi>Hieroboams,</hi> that made all <hi>Iſraell</hi> to ſinne: put the adulterers paines to the bloudy murtherers tortures, and both vnto the Idolaters ſufferings; and whoſe fleſh and bloud is euer able to endure it? Nay ſuppoſe all the paines, that are helliſhly inflicted vpon a whole kingdome of reprobates, were all laid vpon one man: euen ſuch ſhall the puniſhment be of all them, that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes doe diuide: and will not this diſſwade neither? Farther then this we cannot goe, only wee haue acceſſe to him, that can goe farther, by <hi>prayer,</hi> which is the laſt remedy. Among twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Commentators there's one ſayes, <hi>Precemur ergo deum:</hi> O ye that are choſen to collegiate liues; encreaſe ye the number, I beſeech yee: what d'ee thinke, is the primitiue inſtitution of the Founder, or what the expediency of ſuch a pious place? that ye ſhould waxe olde in ſtudying ſuperfluous queſtions of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria prima,</hi> and whether <hi>puncta</hi> be <hi>entia realia in continuo,</hi> or no? admiring only the Man in the Moone, and ſtudying the queſtion, till—as wiſe as he. Yee haue no paſtorall charges to converſe withall: ye are ſequeſter'd from all the World beſide: ye are the only fit men and place for prayer vnto God: O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend this cauſe in your petitions often to his Throne: <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria prae patre:</hi> The Philoſopher was wont to ſay, he loued his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2548:14"/>
dome dearer then his owne father: and I that could make mine owne intereſts (being a ſingle man) vpon foreſight of aduantage as well as others, yet hauing conſcience of the publike, I ſo far preferre my Countries good before mine owne, that I baſeech you all often to pray againſt diuiſion, both in your priuate and publique deuotions vnto God: that it would pleaſe him euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more to preſerue vs from all mercenary penſioners, as hee hath at any time done heretofore, from all falſe Catholiques &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarieties to the truth, from all temptations to rebellion by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine alliance whatſoeuer it be: that hee would ſo direct the kingdomes gouernment, as no reuengefull ſpirit may haue any matter to worke vpon, either within themſelues, or abroad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the multitude of the Commonwealth: you haue your iniunction the 1. Ep. To <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. Chap. 1. ver. <hi>That prayers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions be made for all: for Kings and Kingdomes, and all that are in eminent place, that ſo we may lead a quiet and a peaceable, a peaceable life.</hi> Peace is the fruit of prayer: Peace is the preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the augmentation of the Church: pray therefore that our kingdomes peace faile not; becauſe the preſeruation, the aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation of the Church depends vpon the kingdomes peace: theſe are the cauſes, effects, and remedies, which in a Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call modeſty we can be permitted to declare vnt'ce: other there are more politicall, which if yee knowe them, happy are yee, if yee doe them; <hi>For if a kingdome bee divided againſt it ſelfe that kingdome can neuer ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if yee doe them, receaue <hi>a word of conſolation</hi> to your ſoules, all you that are not guilty of this Nation-falling ſicknes, this kingdome-killing ſinne: you haue neither taken penſion to betray the kingdome, nor for reuenge encouraged others to make a faction in the land: yee haue not for ſchiſme ſake engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred any other religion, then that which is the maine orthodox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of the ſtate: ſollace your ſelues, you can be no cauſes of the kingdomes fall. But yee ſay yee haue beene diſcontented at the preſent ſtate, and that yee feare is diuiſion: you haue ſometimes ſpoken a word againſt the diſorders of the Realme, and that is diuiſion, yee ſeare: yee haue ſaid 'twere good we had warres, &amp; is not that diuiſion too? No I beſeech yee; marke but the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis:
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2548:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
if diuided <hi>againſt it ſelfe!</hi> there is a diuiſion that makes for the good of the whole: ſo the mouthes of Diſputants are many times diuided in purſuit of deliberatiue argument for fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out the truth, and yet they accord well enough in the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſame concluſion all at laſt: and ſuch a diuiſion is like a diuiſion of notes in muſicke: it is not diuided againſt it ſelfe, it makes the ſweeter ſound. Your diſcontented eies guſh out with teares, becauſe men keepe not the law; this is not to make, but marre the diuiſion of a land: your tongue reports vnto the Church ſome diſorders you haue ſeene; but in words of ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt charity; in the abundance of louely deſires, not in any bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe doe yee report the ſame: and ſo peraduenture yee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the euill to bee taken away by man, or pardon'd by God, becauſe yee are ſo zelous againſt the ſinne: in all ſuch eſtates of cauſes the diviſion is not againſt it ſelfe, but for the whole; ſuch a kingdome is not diuided againſt it ſelfe: you deſire warres, but forraine not ciuill warres; and that's no diuiſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelfe, but a firmer vnion of the whole. And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other caſes there are, wherein it is not onely lawfull, but moſt neceſſary to be diuided for the publicke good; and one mans tongue to moue one way, and anothers in a ſecond path, as the Orbes doe in the Firmament: The <hi>primun mobile</hi> runnes Weſt, the next particular Spheares Eaſt, the lower Planets ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely take another courſe: yet all tempering ſweetly together for the commodity of the whole: otherwiſe if they ſhould run all one may, they would hurry the earth and all to peeces, and ſpoyle the naturall growth of all: So runnes the King our <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Mobile,</hi> in motions all aloft: the Nobles as the next Spheares <hi>ſeeme</hi> another way: the Clergie and Courts of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty like the neerer Planets take a third courſe: but all working ſweetly for the commodity of the whole: otherwiſe, if all one way; the Commons which are <hi>terra Reipub:</hi> would be hurryed all to peeces, &amp; it would ſpoile the publique growth of all: You know how <hi>Lucan</hi> deſcribes the ouer-whelming of a Ship: <hi>dum nimium pugnax:</hi> while they ranne all to one ſide topſy-turvy by vnequall poyſe they ouer-weigh'd the Ship: they muſt diuide themſelues therefore, that meane to preſerue the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2548:15"/>
that floating Ship: but ſtill they muſt agree in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſuch a diuiſion very circumſpectly, for the well-fare of the whole: If any man hath bin guilty of indiſcretion to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, let him hereafter temper himſelfe in a wiſer kind: if hee'll endeauour to make vs ſing the 133 Pſalme in a pleaſanter tune then euer we did before: <hi>O how pleaſant a thing it is for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to dwell together in vnity!</hi> then ſhall his preſence bee as acceptable to our eyes, as Muſick it ſelfe is to our eares: O how beautifull is the preſence of them that preſerue peace among vs: Muſicke is no muſick to be compared with that ſweet recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call converſation of body and ſoule, of fleſh and blood, which is moſt liuely diſplayed euery houre betweene each other in time of Peace: Muſicke onely glorifies the eare; but this the whole body of a Kingdome doth adorne: <hi>Tis like the precious oyntment on the head, which runneth downe to the skirts of all the Kingdome:</hi> Muſicke preſerues from Melancholy onely for a while: but this for euermore: <hi>for there the Lord promiſed his bleſſing, and life for euermore:</hi> Muſicke cannot make a litle town a great City: but ſmall and contemptible beginnings haue growne into great Kingdomes by concord, whereas mighty Empires by diuiſion haue bin ouer-turn'd: who then not honour thoſe that doe preſerue our peace? to them the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: Yee haue pray'd againſt diuifion, and there's no ſigne in that of diuiding a Kingdome againſt it ſelfe: ye haue <hi>hated the Societies of the ſeditious,</hi> as the King himſelfe commands, <hi>Prov. 24.21:</hi> and that's no ſigne of diuiding the Kingdome againſt it ſelfe: yee haue ſcorn'd penſion, allyance, reuenge, ambition, all to preſerue the Kingdome in vnity with it ſelfe: you haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeru'd the vnion of the Kingdome, and the vnion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhall preſerue you: you ſhall not be guilty of this foule Kingdome-killing ſinne: But you ſay there are other <hi>deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a Kingdome from without:</hi> 'tis true, yet I neuer loue to wander from my Text: my Text concernes onely <hi>diſſipations within: If a Kingdome be diuided againſt it ſelfe, that kingdome can neuer ſtand:</hi> Wherefore to <hi>ſumme vp all;</hi> whether Princes be diuided againſt themſelues, or Subiects againſt themſelues; or Prince and People one againſt another: whether about ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2548:16"/>
or any other pretenſiue matter of pleaſure, profit, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge: whether the ſubtilty of any other kingdome inſtigate, or they be the beginners of it themſelues: whether it ariſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Clergy, and ſo proceed to the Laitie, or from Laitie to Clergy: howeuer it bee, if it bee abſolutely diuided againſt it ſelfe, it can neuer long ſubſiſt, for it will turne the Phyſutian a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Patient, Sonne againſt Father, Seruant againſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Flocke againſt Miniſter; it turnes tongues and pennes, hearts and hands, ſwords and ſpeares of one againſt another: makes them betray, murther each other behind their backes: diſgrace the meetings, ſolemnities, orders, attributes of each other, and therefore it can neuer ſtand: <hi>a kingdome diuided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelfe can neuer ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to refreſh yee with <hi>another word of ſpeciall application</hi> to the time, and ſo an end: To day is this Scripture doubly fulfill'd in all your eares: had the Court with them, or the Clergy with vs, bin abſolutely diuided againſt the Kingdomes good, the Kingdome had periſht then, the glory of it now; yee had bin both deſtitute of ſuch a King, and ſuch a glorious cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the day: the one well knowne among our ſelues, the other all abroad: For as on this day <hi>Gowrie</hi> and his brother ſet both vpon the King—But GOD gaue the victory, determin'd the queſtion, ſent his ſeruants to reſcue him; and <hi>Ramſay</hi> thruſt <hi>Gowrie</hi> through the heart: he ſtrooke him, &amp; he ſtrooke him dead, and he ſtrooke him dead at a blow, and I am ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what afraide he ſtrooke his ſoule downe dead to hell: For he died in a moment, without crying either to the King or GOD for mercy: —the diuiſion of a Kingdome, of his own king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and that againſt ſo great an Anointed of the Lord, as our Soueraigne is, whoſe Seed was to gouerne in ſo many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulent Kingdomes after him; I ſee the rume of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the confuſion of <hi>Scotland,</hi> the diuiſion of <hi>England,</hi> the ſuppreſſion of all Proteſtant Religion in <hi>Germany,</hi> and what not? all in this one more then Nationall ſinne of <hi>Gowries</hi> Conſpiracy; &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may I not iuſtly feare he ſtrooke his ſoule downe dead to hell? —diuiſions are too-too often in euery State, and that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſmall occaſions many times: what ſayes Traytor <hi>Gowrie</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2548:16"/>
for himſelfe? 'Twas to reuenge his father: to reuenge your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? what, vpon the man that neuer wrong'd your father? vpon the King himſelfe? your father was a tainted man; the King was but in his yong minoritie; a meerely gentle paſſiue in thoſe affaire: They were the Protectors and the hand of Iuſtice cut your father off, 'twas not the King: and if he were iuſtly executed, why ſhould you not endure it? if vniuſtly, yet endure it; for then Heauen would reuenge him without any ſuch ſinfull helpe of yours: your Tutor <hi>Rollocke</hi> (M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>) and a greater then <hi>Rollocke,</hi> what ſaith hee? Tell me ſayes <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> when <hi>Cain</hi> put <hi>Abell</hi> vniuſtly death, which of thoſe two was the dead man? <hi>dic quaeſo uter illorum erat mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us?</hi> whether <hi>Abell,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ad Rom. cap. 4. ſerm. 8.</note> whoſe bloud did after liue to triurnph in a victorious crye, or <hi>Cain</hi> whoſe bloud did after liue in ſeruile feare of euery aſpine leafe? bloud-guilty <hi>Cains</hi> countenance waxt pale, and ſpeechleſſe, and dead, while aliue; but innocent <hi>Abels</hi> bloud was freſh and liuely, &amp; triumphant in a glorious cry: witneſſe the Law; it is the crying child, that doth inioy the ſtate of life, and therefore <hi>Cains</hi> bloud was dead, but <hi>Abels</hi> was aliue, becauſe it cryed vnto the Lord: ſo that if your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were an <hi>Abell,</hi> vniuſtly put to death, then was your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aliue, and being aliue, his bloud ſhould haue commenced the ſuite, his bloud haue ſought reuenge, not you: but being iuſtly executed, much leſſe: Tis reprobat-like to iniure thoſe that iniure you; but pure damnation to iniure thoſe that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer iniur'd you: Is any man culpable? witneſſes are produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; be it the apparence of his own actions, or other mens ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages to condemne him: howeuer if he ſuffer, let him blame the witnes, not the Common-wealth: if he ſeeke reuenge by the diuiſion of a kingdome for it, he iniures thoſe that neuer iniured him, and the height of damnation ſhall bee his due. No, no, there was ſomewhat more then the priuate reuenge of his father that vrged the Traitour to it: he was brought vp in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> the very place where the moſt King-killing doctrine is taught to be the true meaning of the Goſpell: I ſhould miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>report the probability of all ſtory, if I ſhould arraigne Earle <hi>Gowry</hi> for a Praeciſian before yee, rather then a Papiſt in this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2548:17"/>
fact-for he was a notorious Magician; the Characters found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his, ſearcht in the preſence of the King: a very vſuall thing with Papiſts, but where did yee euer know a Praeciſian that was ſo magically giuen? brought vp in <hi>Italy?</hi> common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Papiſts; but where euer Praeciſian that was Italianly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? his plauſible popularity argues him Papiſt, or carnall Proteſtant at leaſt: but where euer ſowre-faced Praeciſian, that was ſo popularly giuen? his daylie complices <hi>Logan</hi> and <hi>Bour,</hi> men of no Religion at all, by <hi>Sprotts</hi> owne <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sprott</hi> at his Arraigment exhorted all to take heed how they kept company with ſuch as made no profeſſion of Religion: acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all, that his haunting ſo much with the Lo: <hi>Logan,</hi> a man without Religion, and ſubiect to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; as alſo his continuall being in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with the Lo: <hi>Bour,</hi> who was as irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious as the other, and without feare of God, had enſnared him thereunto: and therefore he deſired them all againe, to beware of euill company, eſpecially thoſe that were voide of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: they are his owne very words: publiſht by authority.</note> Confeſſion, his diuine correſpondencie with Ieſuits alſo, who did euer know Praeciſian ſo irreligiouſly, ſo Ieſuitically giuen? perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture ſome miſ-praeciſians did adhere too much vnto the faireneſſe of his tongue, becauſe they diſ-affected the Kings E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall gouernment of the Church: peradventure ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed by blood or ſeruice or other affection to the man can not ſo well digeſt the mention of that treaſon vnto this day: peradventure the ignorance of others do to this houre miſtake his intendments, as if they were really belonging to their own ſide; but miſtakes be they neuer ſo many, cannot ſatisfie the arguments alleadged; nor will the nature of the cauſe euer beare it to be defined vpon him as a Praeciſians fact: The hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory is knowne, and I haue heard this pulpit ſpeake ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 14 yeares agoe, that his out-landiſh education was the chiefeſt cauſe of all: For there ye haue the height of all pride; there ye haue profeſt ſchooles and methods of reuenge; there factions are taught by rules, and treaſons by a kinde of Law. I would to God I had but freedome to ſpeake: but what euer the cauſe was, the ſinne is a crying, killing, deadly, damning ſinne: Is this your Catholicke trayning vp of children beyond the ſeas, to prepare them for after-treaſons and diuiſions in a State? Is this your hypocriticall wearing of CHRISTS Croſſe about your neckes, that ſo yee may more cunningly crucifie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? is this the recompence ye returne him for all the merits of his paſſion? How often did he endure the buffetting fiſt, the bloudy ſpeare, and many a tormenting diuiſion more? &amp; why?
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2548:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but that we might liue and flouriſh in the fulneſſe, the fatneſſe of our peace: Peace hee brought downe from Heauen with him: Peace he recommended being about to die: But <hi>Logan</hi> will none of his peace, he ſayes, he will hazard life, lands, and honour; nay, Hell it ſelfe ſhall not affright him, but he will be revenged vpon the King, they are his own words. Not Hell it ſelfe affright him? yes, the griſly ghaſtly lookes of one tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fire-flaming diuell would make his traytorous bones tremble into ſo many ſeuerall anguiſhes, as an Angell-Oratour were neuer able to expreſſe: Irons, fires, chaines, priſons, gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets, wheeles, tortures, yellings, howlings, crucifyings, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery moment they ſuffer the multiplication of a thouſand ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deaths: and that which is the horrour of all, thoſe ſauage ſpiries are ſo furious about them, it ſeemes GOD doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine their malice in that world to come; but they may tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a man beyond all infiniteneſſe, if they will: For doe yee not ſee the wheele vpon them? and the worme that neuer dyes gnawing their conſcience about the heart? doe yee not ſee the fire that neuer goes forth, parching their tongues with burning thirſt? and foule coale-blacke ſprights tearing their fleſh with red-hot iron inſtruments of vengeance for their ſinne? iuſt as they did offer to pull and teare the viſage of the King: O the intollerable painfull puniſhment they doe endurel euery houre a new addition to their old hell! doe yee not he are them cry ſometimes, if yee liſten well about the dead time of the night? for certain it may well be ſome of that company; It any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did depart this world vnrepented of ſo great a ſinne: And ſtill they ſay, oh that they might haue a little eaſe, if it were but a very litle eaſe, if but neuer ſo litle peace with thoſe infernall fiends; they would willingly returne to their former paine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine about an houre after with all their hearts: no, they were full of diuiſion and bloud, and vengeance, and all tormentiue i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations while they were aliue, and therefore it is but iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice now that the full vialls of Gods vengeance ſhould bee powred out vpon them.</p>
            <p>Beware ye ſpirits of ſedition, that yee come not to this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning lake: doe not effect thoſe out-landiſh faſhions of ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2548:18"/>
and reuenge: Tis not your characters of Magicke can ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you from the paines of hell, no nor from ſtroake of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neither, if ye deſerue the blow: diuiſion of any kingdome is a deadly ſinne, but the greater, if your owne; and in your owne the greateſt is againſt the King: ſeauen times hotter ſhall be your hell: if hee were reprobate, yet your God on earth; but being regenerate, he partakes the bloud-royall of IESVS CHRIST himſelfe: for him yee muſt fight, as on this day loyall <hi>Ramſay</hi> did; for him giue thankes, for him pray: Come I beſeech you, and let vs binde our ſelues againe by faith and Sacrament vnto him: by prayers wee'll be his thundring Army, and if need require, thoſe your faire learned hands ſhall be his Praetorian band; faithfull to the death! with whom can yee be in charity, if not with him? you deſired the preheminence ſhould bee taken from your ſiſter, and beſtowed vpon your ſelues; it was ſo: a new reformation by Parliament ye did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; to that his Maieſty did conſent: you deſired the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of old debts, it was ſo: that exceſſiue bands of Vſury might be releaſed, to that alſo he did conſent: one while you deſired there might be peace in your owne dayes, and it was ſo; another-while warre, and to that alſo he did conſent: one while to be ſtewards of your owne lands and moneyes; it was ſo: another-while commanders of your owne waters, &amp; thereto alſo he did conſent: Now what can he doe more for his Vineyard, that he hath not done? euen that alſo ſhal be perfited in after-time: Wherefore, long may he rule ouer vs, and neuer too long may we obey his proſperous raigne; and liuing in v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie one with another, <hi>Let the world grow olds, but neuer this Kingdome know what diuiſion meanes:</hi> If yee agree, no hoſtile power ſhall vnarme yee; if diuide, euery ſmall enemie ſhall take your kingdome from ye: giue me your ſpeares, giue me ſtrong cords, and I will breake them before your faces, if yee diuide them; but keepe them vnited, and <hi>Sampſon</hi> himſelfe ſhall not doe the deed.</p>
            <p>The time commands mee: take only S. <hi>Bernard</hi> with ye, &amp; I haue done: <hi>Ante mihi contingat mori, quam audire in vobis aliquem iuſtè clamantem; fily matris meae pugnaverunt contra
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2548:18"/>
me</hi> Let me die, ere euer I heare any man iuſtly complaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ye, that the ſonnes of his owne mother haue fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. Yee are all children of the ſame Kingdome, of the ſame Congregation all; and all brothers to each other; neither is any man ſo like himſelfe in all things, as yee are all in ſome things like to one another: Loue therefore but within your ſelues; nothing without yee ſhall euer be preiudiciall vnt'ee: the 29 Serm: on the <hi>Canticles.</hi> —O thou heauenly concord, that dwelleſt aboue the Orbes, deſcend into the hearts of ſuch as heare me this day: or giue them concord, or elſe thou blotteſt me out of the booke of life; or giue them concord, or elſe thou wilt diuide mee; or giue them concord, or elſe wee all ſhall die: Heare vs good Lord, and anſwere vs according to the multitude of thy mercies for IESVS CHRISTS ſake, to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be all honour and glory now and euermore, AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
